Boker tov בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, Shana Tova שנה טובה *Shana Tova*.
Today's daf דף daf. *daf* is Yud Aleph יא *Yud Aleph* of
11, we pick up at the bottom of Yud Amud Bet י
עמוד ב Yud Amud Bet. *Yud Amud Bet*. We're in the middle
of discussing the issue about we first dealt with a rabbinic kinyan
קניין kinyan. *kinyan* of arba amos ארבע אמות arba amot. *arba amos*,
something within your four amos, within your personal space. It seemed to
the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that it was clearly a type of
a conceptually a type of a chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer*. But that
then led us to discussing what the nature of chatzer חצר chatzer.
*chatzer* is. Why does this chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer* work? And it
started with the question about whether a minor girl who you can
put a get גט get *get* into her on her person, and
presumably in her chatzer חצר chatzer, *chatzer*, we'll get to that in
a minute. Anyway, so whether that whether she also has a chatzer
חצר chatzer *chatzer*, and if she has a chatzer חצר chatzer. *chatzer*
then she would have arba amos ארבע אמות *arba amos* as a,
she not have a chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer*. And the Gemara's גמרא
Gemara *Gemara's* framing of this question is, well why does chatzer חצר
chatzer *chatzer* work? Is chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer* seen as an extension
of yourself, a yad יד yad, *yad*? It's like putting something on
my property is putting it on my person, and then it would
obviously apply to minors this way. Or is it seen as somehow
acting in my behalf, which is a funny anthropomorphic idea? It is
holding on and possessing it, and because it's mine and my field
is possessing it, it works for me. So that's a kind of
a concept of shlichus שליחות shlichus *shlichus*. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* said a difference between so the first question the Gemara גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* asks is, well one minute, then how can you use
your chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer* to be a gannav גנב *gannav*? Something
walks into your yard and you close the gate with intention to
steal it. Ein shaliach l'dvar aveirah אין שליח לדבר עבירה Ein Shaliach
l'Dvar Aveirah *Ein shaliach l'dvar aveirah*. If we're really going to take
the concept of shlichus שליחות shlichus *shlichus* seriously. So the Gemara גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* has two responses to this. Why is there no ein
shaliach l'dvar aveirah אין שליח לדבר עבירה Ein Shaliach l'Dvar Aveirah? *ein
shaliach l'dvar aveirah*? Because the shaliach שליח Shaliach, *shaliach* shouldn't be doing
it, because he's accountable for his own actions. Well, that's limited to
the case when a shaliach שליח Shaliach, *shaliach* is obligated. A chatzer
חצר chatzer *chatzer* doesn't have an obligation in the same way God
didn't say lo tignov לא תגנוב *lo tignov* and lo tirtzach לא
תרצח *lo tirtzach* and kabbad et avicha כבד את אביך *kabbad et
avicha* to the angel, right? Because you don't have angels and you
don't steal, so he didn't say it to the chatzer חצר chatzer
*chatzer* either. Okay, so they're not obligated in these mitzvot מצוות *mitzvot*.
So the chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer*, so therefore there's no idea that
it is
somehow shouldn't be doing it. Again, it's quite anthropomorphic. And therefore it's
not a problem of shaliach l'dvar aveirah שליח לדבר עבירה Shaliach l'Dvar
Aveirah *shaliach l'dvar aveirah*. The other answer was that it didn't have
any choice. Normal person you should have chosen otherwise. Divrei harav v'divrei
hatalmid, divrei mi shome'im דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד, דברי מי שומעים *Divrei
harav v'divrei hatalmid, divrei mi shome'im*? God says don't do it, the
guy told you to do it, who do you listen to? Anyway,
the chatzer חצר chatzer *chatzer* didn't have any choice, it's not acting
on its own agency. So therefore it can be a shaliach שליח
Shaliach, *shaliach* when it does something you are held responsible. If it's
gonev גונב *gonev* for you, you're held responsible, because it is always
seen it is never seen as sort of acting on its own,
it's always acting on your behalf because it does not have a
choice. So those are the two reasons why we can apply this
concept of shlichus שליחות shlichus *shlichus* and it's not a problem that
the chatzer חצר chatzer, *chatzer* does a gneva גניבה *gneva* for me,
because it's not obligated or because it does not have choice and
therefore it is therefore it's not seen as acting on its own
and in acting in violation. One second. Now, the Gemara's גמרא Gemara
*Gemara's* going to continue with this and sort of have some interesting,
I guess we'll see the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as it continues
with this. Okay, I guess we'll see the next case in the
Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. What I'll just say for this moment is
that although you can see there's a mishna משנה mishna, *mishna* coming
up, this idea of sort of how do you conceptualize chatzer חצר
chatzer *chatzer* and is it a shliach שליח Shaliach *shliach* and is
it a yad יד yad *yad* is actually going to also going
to be what dominates the whole next daf דף daf? *daf* and
the whole next discussion of the next mishna משנה mishna. *mishna*. So
we're going to be sort of wrapping up this whole discussion over
the course of today. Michael, what's your question?
Regarding the arba amos ארבע אמות *arba amos* kones קונה koneh *kones*,
do they have to explicitly interpret like the previous mishna משנה mishna.
*mishna* too then? Like, you know, when this guy's m'heiman מהימן *m'heiman*,
when he tells your friend to go and do it. So all
that was I learn as the rish רישא *rish* or you just
didn't say, I'm
zoche זוכה *zoche*.
Yeah, that's what the Gemara
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
no, and zoche זוכה *zoche* because you fell on it or whatever.
All those answers the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gave.
No, but me saying your arba amos ארבע אמות *arba amos*, you
don't have to fall on it at all.
Meaning, you told your friend I'm zoche זוכה *zoche*. Yeah, yeah, that's
what the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said, correct. Okay. Yeah, Dov. Can
a katan
קטן katan.
*katan* have possession?
A katan קטן katan *katan* can own, a katana קטנה ketana *katana*
can have a yad
יד yad *yad* for holding something.
She can't take possession of something,
but are you asking about how even if I put something in
a katan's קטן katan *katan's* hand that they would own it?
Yeah, that's true.
Well, they can't be koneh קונה koneh *koneh* something from hefker הפקר
*hefker*, whether they can be koneh קונה koneh. *koneh* something when da'as
acheres makneh oso דעת אחרת מקנה daas acheres makneh, אותו *da'as acheres
makneh oso*, when I'm transferring it to a katan קטן katan *katan*
and I put it in his hand, does that work biblically or
only rabbinically? That's a debate. But it does work, it certainly works
by a get גט get *get* because by the get גט get
*get* the Torah, I mean, that was the question also that generated
the other day, how much by a get גט get, *get* is
it an idea of being makneh מקנה makne *makneh* the get גט
get, *get*, being transferring ownership of the get גט get *get* or
how much is it just an idea of putting the get גט
get *get* on, transmitting the get גט get, *get* and putting it
on the person. So let's we'll come back to the katan קטן
katan. *katan* and the katana קטנה ktana, *katana* case, but that's the
right question to ask. Let's continue in the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the following on the bottom
of Yud Amud Bet י עמוד ב beis, *Yud Amud
Bet*.
Mai beinaihu מאי בינייהו Mai Binaihu? *Mai beinaihu*? It is three, seven
lines before the lines get wide, last two words of the line.
What is the difference between whether the reason of ein shaliach l'dvar
aveirah אין שליח לדבר עבירה Ein Shaliach l'Dvar Aveirah. *ein shaliach l'dvar
aveirah* is because the guy... Let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So
the גמרא Gemara. says the following on the bottom of י' עמוד
ב'. מאי בינייהו? It is three, seven lines before the lines get
wide, last two words of the line. What is the difference between
whether the reason of אין שליח לדבר עבירה ein shaliach lidvar aveira,
is because the guy was obligated, the שליח, Shaliach and he shouldn't
have violated by doing it, so because he shouldn't be doing it,
he's not my שליח, shaliach or because he had a choice, regardless
of whether he was obligated or not? What's the difference between those
concepts of אין שליח לדבר עבירה? ein shaliach lidvar aveira, איכא בינייהו
Ika Binaihu and now we're going to go, now it's become a
fascinating discussion of שליח לדבר עבירה shaliach lidvar aveira and we're putting
חצרו Chatzero aside for a moment. איכא בינייהו Ika Binaihu כהן Kohen
דאמר ליה לישראל זיל וקדש לי אשה גרושה. d'amar lei l'Yisrael zil
v'kadesh li isha grusha. A כהן Kohen says to a ישראל, Yisrael,
go for me, marry me this divorced woman. Okay, so this, if
the ישראל Yisrael were to do it for the כהן, Kohen, he
would sort of be over on לפני עור לא תתן מכשול Lifnei
Iver lo titen Michshol because he's helping the כהן Kohen do an
עבירה, aveirah, but he is not actually himself prohibited to marry a
divorced woman.
לפני עור לא תתן מכשול
Lifnei
Iver lo
titen Michshol if he tells you to do it?
Yeah. Well, yeah, there's some, the classic cases of לפני עור Lifnei
Iver in the גמרא Gemara are amazing cases. I understand your question,
but we're moving on. Okay,
אינמי Inami איש דאמר לה לאשה אקפי לי קטן, Ish d'amar lah
l'isha akpi li katan, go cut off the פאות payos of that
קטן. katan Now, because the same way a person is not allowed,
a man is not allowed to cut his own פאות payos off,
not פאות, payos, whatever, not the things that the חסידים Chasidim have,
but the sideburns, you're not allowed to cut off the sideburns, you're
also you're not allowed to cut the sideburns of a man or
of a boy. Okay, so a woman is not in the prohibition
of doing of having them cut or doing the cutting. Okay, so
if a woman on her own would cut the sideburns of a
boy, she would actually not transgress anything and the boy wouldn't because
he's a minor. But if the man said to the woman, go
and do it for me, so she herself is not prohibited and
is actually not even doing a prohibition, and it's even better than
the כהן Kohen and the גרושה grusha case because it's not even
a לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. She's not causing anybody to be נכשל,
nichshal, right? But if she's seen as an extension of the man
who sent her, then the man is doing the עבירה, aveirah, the
man has now through the woman transgressed. Now, an interesting question of
יש שליח לדבר עבירה Yesh Shaliach l'Dvar Aveirah is, would that mean
we would give the guy lashes? I mean, he was, is he
considered as if he actually directly cut off, did the עבירה aveirah
with his own hands? Or is it more like he caused the
עבירה aveirah to be done and he somehow is sort of liable
בדיני שמים b'dinei shamayim as it were, but not so much that
he actually did it directly and personally? How far do we take
this idea of יש שליח לדבר עבירה? Yesh Shaliach l'Dvar Aveirah? Because
normally you understand the concept of שליחות shlichus, is not a question
of whether I did the physical action, the concept of שליחות shlichus
is normally a question of whether you can, of whether the legal
act that you do will be binding for me. You marry a
woman for me, you sell my field, you buy my field, right?
Will it take legal effect? Here, we're not talking about legal effect.
Here, the reality is the sideburns are cut off. The question is,
is it like I physically did it in order that I tell
you to take my לולב, Lulav, I didn't take a לולב, Lulav,
right? So if I tell you to do an עבירה, aveirah, so
that's an interesting question, even if יש שליח לדבר עבירה Yesh Shaliach
l'Dvar Aveirah in this case, how much are we really saying it's
like this person physically did it? Okay, so one of the cases
of a, so that's anyway but that's the question. So let's see
how the גמרא Gemara says, what they'll take the question is in
the middle, let's see how the גמרא Gemara frames it. להאי לישנא
דאמר כל היכא דבעי עביד ובעי לא עביד, L'hai lishna d'amar kol
hacha d'baei avid u'baei lo avid,
if the issue that is making you an independent agent, you're not
seen as working for this guy because you could choose to do
it or not, so לא מיחייב שולחו, lo mechayev sholcho, then I'm
not obligated if I go and tell you marry me this divorced
woman or give a haircut to this minor. Because even though you
could say, hey, no problem me giving a haircut, that's totally fine,
nevertheless, you shouldn't be doing it on my behalf. I'm obligated not
to do it, you shouldn't be doing it on my behalf, and
you have a choice. So since you have a
choice and you shouldn't be doing it, it's not me, it's you
who's doing it, you had the choice, you're the agent, I'm not
the agent, I'm not forcing you to do it. Which raises an
interesting question that Jenna raised the other day after the שיעור shiur
ended, which is let's say I'm holding a gun to your head
and I'm saying,
go give a haircut to this minor, I'm saying to do any
עבירה, aveirah, go steal this thing from me or else I'll kill
you, right? So there you don't really have a choice. So how
much in that case would we say יש שליח לדבר עבירה? Yesh
Shaliach l'Dvar Aveirah? But as long as I have a choice, as
long as I'm not the שליח, shaliach I'm the משלח. Meshaleach. As
long as Michael has a choice whether to do it or not,
or Jenna, she'll be the one giving the haircut to the minor,
then it's never me who's doing it, she's a free agent, she's
the one who's doing it, אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shaliach lidvar
aveira הכא נמי אי בעי עביד ואי בעי לא עביד לא מיחייב
שולחו, Hacha nami ei baei avid v'ei baei lo avid lo mechayev
sholcho, so
if that's the issue, so here Jenna can choose whether to give
the haircut or not, even though there's no prohibition for her to
do it, but she's always acting on her own, she's not acting
for me.
להאי לישנא דאמרת כל היכא דשליח לאו בר חיובא מיחייב שולחו, L'hai
lishna d'amrat kol hacha d'shaliach lav bar chiyuva mechayev sholcho, but if
you say that if the שליח shaliach is not obligated, then the
משלח Meshaleach is liable, because then the שליח shaliach is not doing
any violation and is not bound by this prohibition and therefore there's
no reason not to do it, and therefore it is considered שליחות
shlichus? and that's why the חצר chatzer works. So הכא נמי כיון
דלאו בני חיובא Hacha nami keivan d'lav bnei chiyuva So הכא נמי,
hachanami, כיון דלאו בני חיובא נינהו, keivan d'lav bnei chiyuva ninhu, since
Jenna is not obligated not to give a haircut to that minor,
מהני שליחות, mahani shlichus,
then she is acting on my behalf. There's nothing that's telling her
she shouldn't do it, and therefore since she would be acting on
my behalf and I would be חייב. chayav. Okay now it is
funny because as תוספות Tosafot points out, the קטן katan. case is
the better case. The כהן Kohen case is even if she's not,
even if I'm the כהן Kohen and even if Jenna is not
obligated for two reasons not to marry a גרושה. grusha. א, alef,
she's not a כהן, Kohen, and ב, she's a woman. Okay so
nevertheless, but she still shouldn't be doing it because of לפני עור.
lifnei iver. Right, she is making it that this woman is like
married to me, and how much is that a type of לפני
עור? lifnei iver? But I guess if you say if it's not
going to be effective or not, right, then maybe it's not לפני
עור. lifnei iver. So this leads תוספות Tosafot to a fascinating question.
When we say, not necessarily, תוספות Tosafot questions if we would say
אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein shaliach lidvar aveira
then maybe the קידושין kiddushin didn't take effect. I mean the קטן's
katan, sideburns will still be cut
off, okay, but if you're saying that there's no שליחות, shlichus maybe
that doesn't only mean that I'm not liable for having married this
divorced woman, maybe that really means that
because there's no
שליחות shlichus then the קידושין kiddushin did not work. So there's a
famous תשובה tshuva of the נודע ביהודה Noda Biyehuda that the case
was a man made a שליח shaliach. to deliver a גט get.
to his wife against his wife's
will, even though there's חרם רבנו גרשום, cherem Rabbeinu Gershom, and the
שליח shaliach. went ahead and did it. So the question is the
following: number one, is it a שליח לדבר עבירה shaliach lidvar aveira
to tell somebody to violate חרם רבנו גרשום? cherem Rabbeinu Gershom? What
constitutes דבר עבירה, dvar aveira, right? It's not a מצוה mitzvah of
the תורה, Torah, it's not a מצוה דאורייתא, mitzvah d'Oraisa, it's חרם
רבנו גרשום. cherem Rabbeinu Gershom. Is that a דבר עבירה? dvar aveira?
And number two is the שליח shaliach, went and did it, so
is the wife בדיעבד bdiavad divorced or not? Or do you say
שליח shaliach? לדבר עבירה aveira, is מבטל mevatel the שליחות? shlichus So
it's not just a question whether I am liable and do I
get punished, it's a question about whether the שליחות shlichus, is viable.
So it's a classic תשובה tshuva of the נודע ביהודה, Noda Biyehuda,
he works through this whole סוגיא. sugya. Okay so anyway but these
are the two, I don't remember, but תוספות Tosafot is the first
to raise the
question and the גמרא Gemara says, so number one, if you say
אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein shaliach lidvar aveira is the effect of
the שליחות shlichus still there, it's just you're not punished, or the
whole שליחות shlichus is בטל batel so the woman wouldn't be married?
And is the reason אין שליח shaliach, לדבר עבירה aveira. because a
person has free choice not to do it, or because the person
is not obligated? And the גמרא Gemara here gives these two נפקא
מינהs. nafka mina Do you have a question?
It has nothing to do with the content. Is there one place
where the תקנות takanos of חרם רבנו גרשום cherem Rabbeinu Gershom are
collected and explicated?
I don't know if it's all in one place, anyway I
can yes, but let's talk about what's on the דף. Was there
any, I thought you had a question about something on the דף?
No? Okay fine. All right so let's continue. So this is a
classic סוגיא sugya of אין שליח shaliach לדבר עבירה aveira with real
potential נפקא מינהs. nafka mina Okay it still doesn't explain in my
mind why if Jenna goes ahead and marries this divorced woman for
me and you say well she's not a בר חיובא bar chiyuva
so there is a good שליחות, shlichus, she still, so now she
helped me do an עבירה, aveira. right? Now I as the כהן
Kohen have now, so why don't you say it should be אסור
assur because of לפני עור? lifnei iver? And in fact any case
of אין שליח לדבר עבירה aveira it could always be if
you say there will be שליחות shlichus because in this case the
person isn't a בר חיובא, bar chiyuva, but if the שליחות shlichus
is effective it means they made me do an עבירה. So if
they made me do an עבירה then they were doing an עבירה.
So it's
I know, so it's a little bit funny why just because the
שליח is not obligated in the מצוה mitzvah per se that enables
them, it means somehow it means that there's still a viability to
the שליחות, shlichut they're not completely out of the status of being
a שליח.
Is the problem the concept of שליחו של אדם כמותו? shlucho shel
adam kimoiso? Right. That's just right.
I mean in addition the issue here is that שליחות shlichut as
I said is normally about your acts being legally binding for me
as opposed to taking legal effect for me, whereas here when you
talk about עבירה it's also a question did I physically do it
and am I therefore liable for punishment which is normally not the
concept of שליחות to begin with. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
continues, back to חצר. chatzer, ומי איכא למאן דאמר, u'mi ika l'man
d'amar, second wide line from the bottom, ומי איכא למאן דאמר חצר
לאו
משום ידיה אתרבאי, u'mi ika l'man d'amar chatzer lav mishum yadeia itrabai,
one minute and does anybody say that the חצר chatzer. for a
woman or for a girl is not seen as an extension of
her hand?
והתניא, ve'hatanya, ידה, yada, it says by the גט get, it says
ונתן בידה, ve'nasan b'yada, put it in her hand. אין לי אלא
ידה, ein li ela yada, I only know her hand. גג חצר
וקרפיף מנין, gag chatzer ve'karpif minayin, how do I know even in
her yard? תלמוד לומר ונתן מכל מקום, talmud lomar ve'nasan mikol makom,
somehow because it could have said בידה יתננו, b'yada yitnenu, רש"י Rashi
says it says the verb first that means even not directly in
her hand. But nevertheless conceptually what we're saying is that יד, yad,
it's learned it's an extension of the פסוק pasuk about the word
יד yad. and therefore clearly it's based on יד yad, and also
the way תוספות Tosafot points out since you also can give a
גט get to a קטנה ktana and that's included in this פסוק
pasuk and it's saying that you could put it in her. her
חצר, chatzer, so clearly it works because it's a type of a
יד, yad, not because it's a type of a שליח. So גמרא
Gemara says fine. לעניין גט כולי עלמא לא פליגי דחצר משום יד
איתרבאי. Le'inyan get kuli alma lo pligi de'chatzer mishum yad itrabai. Nobody
debates the idea that when it comes to a גט, get a
חצר chatzer is going to work as a type of a יד.
yad, כי פליגי לעניין מציאה. Ki pligi le'inyan metziah. The question is
when it comes to lost objects. מר סבר ילפינן מציאה מגט. Mar
savar yalfinan metziah miget.
One says that we learn out מציאה metziah from a גט, get
and the same way if by גט get it works by a
יד, yad by all areas it'll work like a יד, yad, and
therefore even a קטנה, ktana a young girl could be קונה koneh,
if a מציאה metziah falls in her חצר. chatzer, ומר סבר לא
ילפינן מציאה מגט. U'mar savar lo yalfinan metziah miget. No, by a
גט get, the תורה Torah tells you it works by a יד,
yad, by other areas it does not. Alright, now, ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it
eima, I'll read the whole thing and then I'll say something about
it. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, בקטנה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דילפינן מציאה
מגט. Biktana kuli alma lo pligi deyalfinan metziah miget. By a קטנה
ktana, where the תורה Torah was מחדש mechadesh that their, that her
חצר chatzer is her יד yad, for a גט, get well once
it's מחדש mechadesh that her חצר chatzer. is her יד, yad. so
then it'll work in other areas of קניינים kinyanim as well. And
for all areas for this girl her חצר chatzer, will operate as
her יד, yad even if it's about finding lost objects, and presumably
for a woman as well. והכא בקטן קמיפלגי. Ve'hacha bekatan kamiflagi. The
question is about a young boy, right? Where again there's no concept
of שליחות by minors.
מר סבר ילפינן קטן מקטנה. Mar savar yalfinan katan miktana. The same
way for קטנה ktana, it works as a יד, yad? for קטן
katan. it should logically work as a
יד. yad, ומר סבר לא ילפינן קטן מקטנה. U'mar savar lo yalfinan
katan miktana. No, actually it only works for girls and women presumably,
there there's a concept that the חצר chatzer. has to be a
יד yad. because that's what we need to see it as for
purposes of גט. get, Okay,
whereas by boys it does not work that way. Presumably by men,
I don't know, by man is it שליחות or is it יד?
yad, Maybe it doesn't matter.
Okay. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want I could say מר
מר חדא ומר חדא ולא פליגי. Mar mar chada u'mar chada velo
pligi. They're not really debating. The one that says that a חצר
chatzer, works is talking about a קטנה, ktana, the one that says
it doesn't work is talking about a קטן. katan Or the one
that says it works is talking about גט, get? the one that
says it doesn't work is talking about מציאה, metziah, and maybe there's
no real debate. Now this is all very strange, because once the
תורה Torah tells you in one area we look at a חצר
chatzer. as a יד, yad. presumably we could look at that in
all areas. Okay, we're going to find out as what, when we
start the, you know, when we turn to the next משנה, mishna.
that there might be, you know what, I'll just ruin the surprise
right now, that
there might be extra criteria if we want to look at it
as a יד. yad, The גמרא Gemara is actually going to say
if you want to look at it as a יד, yad the
person has to be standing in or near their חצר chatzer. for
us to look at it as an extension of them. But if
they're in some different place, and you know, and the חצר is
a mile away, you can only look at it as a שליח,
not as a יד. yad. Okay, so we're going to get to
that in a minute. But the point is once the תורה Torah
is מחדש mechadesh that under certain circumstances it can operate as a
יד, yad. if it can operate as a יד yad for a
woman and for a גט get and for a קטנה, ktana then
logically that should be true, you know, for all people. Maybe קטן
katan is a חידוש, chiddush, but you know, at least for a
man it should operate as a יד. yad, Like the idea that
we should distinguish and we should distinguish between גט get, and מציאה
metziah is pretty strange. Unless of course you say the point that
Jenna made the other day, which is maybe גט get is really
not about קניין. kinyan Maybe גט get, is about putting on somebody's
person. So if the whole goal was to put it on somebody's
person, then putting it in their חצר, that would count. But if
the need is actually to take possession, then maybe חצר doesn't operate
as יד. yad Maybe it only operates as יד yad for things,
for גט, for things that the whole need is just to be
on my person. But when there's a need to actually take possession,
maybe it's not enough to call it my יד, yad you need
it to operate in a different type of a way. So it's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara can consider that it definitely works as
a יד yad in some circumstances, גט and a קטנה, ktana but
maybe not in others. Maybe not in מציאה, metziah, maybe not in
a קטן. katan Now the other thing to note here and then
we'll continue on is that the גמרא Gemara does not talk about
the case of me being מקנה something to a קטן, katan. to,
to a קטן. katan Like putting something in a קטן's katan יד
yad, for the purpose of him being קונה koneh or a קטנה's
ktana יד yad. for the purpose of her being קונה. koneh. It
talks about a מציאה. metziah. And as תוספות Tosafot points out and
as was raised yesterday and as was raised the beginning of today,
a קטן katan really cannot be קונה מציאה דאורייתא, koneh metziah d'oraita,
only דרבנן. d'rabanan. If he don't, if he doesn't have anybody else's
דעת da'at that's being provided, then there's no דאורייתא קניין d'oraita kinyan
here at all. It's all דרבנן, d'rabanan, right, for a קטן with
a מציאה. metziah. So maybe that's why the גמרא Gemara is conflicted
about whether a חצר works for מציאה metziah for a קטנה ktana,
and for a קטן. You know, because there what you're also lacking
there is the necessary דעת. da'at. Right, but maybe if I were
trying to put it in a קטנה's ktana יד yad? or put
it in a קטן's יד, yad. then of course it should work.
Alright, so that's what we're left with. The גמרא Gemara, sort of
leaving us as an open question in general, if חצר משום שליח
או משום יד? chatzer mishum shaliach o mishum yad? By a case
of a גט, we have no question that it works as a
type of a יד. yad Okay, it's not exactly clear how we
conceptualize it in קניינים. kinyanim. Do we also conceptualize it as יד?
yad Or do we conceptualize it as שליח? What might be some
נפקא מינהs? nafka mina We'll see in a minute. And therefore, it's
also not clear about whether we would apply it to minors in
a case of מציאה metziah where there's no דעת. da'at. Would we
apply it to a קטן who doesn't have the פרשה parsha of
גט? But the one thing we know for sure is that for
women. And for a קטנה, it works as a type of a
יד. yad. Okay, where else it might work and whether other places
it's a יד or a שליח, that we don't know and that
we'll keep that in mind as we now turn to the next
משנה. mishna. So let's turn to the next משנה. mishna Everybody clear
or clear enough? Okay. There's a lot of unanswered questions.
But the קטנה with the גט in the חצר, so you don't
need דעת. daas. You know, there's a
פסוק. pasuk.
For the גט, correct.
So it's very interesting, right? You know, that you can have that
case where דעת daas all of a sudden, which is such a
primary category in this in the establishment.
Well, גט has two issues. A, it is a דעת daas. אחרת
מקנה, the husband is the one providing the דעת. daas, And number
two is that it might not require קנין, kinyan, it might just
require placing it on somebody's person. Yeah.
The only other נפקא מינה nafka mina I guess, I don't know
if it makes a difference or not because we
also differentiate between חצר המשתמרת chatzer hamishtameres versus the...
Okay, well you know what? That's exactly the next משנה. mishna But
but but place go along with this, but you could say either
way it wouldn't work, because if it's not משתמרת mishtameres and it's
not your יד because my hand doesn't hover over my...
Right, so let's talk about that as soon as we read the
next משנה. mishna Okay, ראוהן רצין אחר מציאה. ra'uhan ratzin achar metzia.
So this was a perfect lead-in to the next discussion. So you
saw two people running after מציאה. metzia. Okay, what would be they
would be running after מציאה? metzia? It could be
an iPhone that's rolling, a soccer ball that's rolling or whatever. או
אחר צבי שבור, o achar tzvi shavur, let's say they were running
after a deer with a broken leg so there's a chance they
might catch it. או אחר גוזלות שלא פרחו, o achar gozalot shelo
parchu, or after little chicks that have not yet begun to fly,
so they might catch it. ואמר, ve'amar, and they're running through your
yard and you say זכתה לי שדי. zachata li sadi. Okay, they're
running through my yard, my field is קונה, koneh, I got the
מציאה metzia first.
You're looking out the window, in that case זכתה לו. zachata lo.
Good. You were קונה koneh, it first. Okay, again, it doesn't matter
they saw it first, it doesn't matter they were running after it
first. You are the first one to do a קנין kinyan because
it was in your yard, so you're
קונה. koneh היה צבי רץ כדרכו, haya tzvi ratz kedarko, however, if
the deer was running with not broken leg, you know, או שהיו
גוזלות מפריחין, o shehayu gozalot mafrihin, or the chicks or the birds
were able to fly, ואמר זכתה לי שדי לא אמר כלום, ve'amar
zachata li sadi lo amar klum, and you said my field is
קונה, koneh you don't say anything because this is telling you you
can't do a קנין חצר kinyan chatzer if the thing cannot won't
stay in your חצר. Okay now we're going to sort of spell
that out in the גמרא. Gemara Let's take a look in the
גמרא. Gemara אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, והוא
שעומד בצד שדהו. vehu she'omed betzad sadehu.
Okay,
you have to be standing near your field. Now at this stage
we think the reason is, is because this is obviously the case
in the משנה mishna where you are קונה, koneh, where there's a
deer with a broken leg. So presumably the reason is similar at
this stage we're going to think it's similar to the reason why
it's not you're not קונה koneh, if the deer is running normally,
because even with a broken leg it could still get out of
the חצר, right? So if the way a חצר is קונה koneh,
is that it's somehow is held within the חצר, you need two
things. You need that there be a broken leg and you need
the idea
that I have the ability to prevent it from escaping. Okay, maybe
if there was a fence around it, okay, and I wasn't עומד
בצד שדהו, omed betzad sadehu, I don't know how it got in
with there being a fence, but let's not worry about that right
now. Somebody threw the deer in or whatever, but now it can't
get out because there's a fence around, okay, or somebody else locked
the fence, whatever the case might be. Then in that case you
would presumably not need עומד בצד שדהו omed betzad sadehu because it's
being held within the field. Okay, so at this stage we're going
to think עומד בצד שדהו omed betzad sadehu is to make it
considered held and potentially, you know, within the field. Again, I could
not run after it and it could get out, but I have
the potential of keeping it within, that's the קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer.
Later we will see that עומד בצד שדהו omed betzad sadehu might
be serving a more formal function of defining the field as my
יד. Okay, but right now presumably it's doing the same it's doing
the job of the broken leg and adding to it and making
sure that the thing is considered held within my field. והוא שעומד
בצד שדהו. vehu she'omed betzad sadehu. So now the גמרא Gemara says
ותקני ליה שדהו. veticni leh sadehu. One minute, why do you need
that? Let's just let the field work for you without you standing
there. דאמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, de'amar Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina, because
רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yossi bar Chanina says, חצרו של אדם
קונה לו שלא מדעתו. chatzero shel adam konah lo shelo mida'ato. A
person's yard works for him even without his דעת, da'at which also
could raise a question of why the משנה Mishnah, says that you
say זכתה לי שדי. zachata li sadi. Why the משנה mishna has
to say you said it? So תוספות Tosafot actually says that's לאו
דווקא. lav davka. We saw before about the whole case by the
גמרא Gemara by the ארבע אמות. You don't have to say you're
being קונה, koneh okay, things it will work for yourself. Okay, so
number one, that means when in the משנה where the guy said
let my field be קונה, koneh you didn't even really need to
say that. But now the גמרא Gemara is saying but why do
you need to be standing by the field? Your field should work
even if you're not there and even without your intention.
So חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו. chatzero shel adam konah
lo shelo mida'ato. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הני מילי בחצר
המשתמרת. hani milei bechatzer hamishtameres. That's if the field is such that
it protects the things within it, that the things within it are
contained, you know, within it. אבל חצר שאינה משתמרת, aval chatzer she'einah
mishtameres, a field that is not protected, so like this case if
the if the deer could just run out on its own, so
אי עומד בצד שדהו אין אי לא לא. ei omed betzad sadehu
in ei lo lo. אין אי לא לא, Ein Ee Lo Lo,
only if you're standing there. So presumably, as I said before, your
standing there makes it משתמרת. Mishtameret. So presumably here, we're all on
the same axis. If the deer is not limping, it's not משתמרת
Mishtameret because it's going to escape. If it is limping, it has
the potential of being משתמרת, Mishtameret, but only if you've either got
a fence around the field or you're standing near the field. But
if neither of those are true, then it's again, it's all a
problem that the thing is not held within the field, it's not
משתמרת. Mishtameret. Okay, but once you're standing there, now presumably, and that
okay, so then it works. Okay, fine. So but now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ומנא תימא, U’mina Teima, where do I know
דחצר שאינה משתמרת Dechatzer She’eina Mishtameret יומד בצד שדהו אין אי לא
לא, Yomed Betzad Sadehu Ein Ee Lo Lo, that if it's not
משתמרת Mishtameret only if you're standing by your field, it works and
if not not? דתניא, Detanya, by the way, because we are thinking
that this is all based on the axis of משתמרת, Mishtameret, if
you were standing by your field but you couldn't still be משמר
Meshamer it, right? Let's imagine, you know, that the deer was at
one end you have a big property, you know, you have acres
of your field and the deer is way at the other end
and could easily escape and you're standing at one end, the opposite
end of your field. Presumably that wouldn't work. It's not some formal
הלכה Halacha of עומד בצד שדהו. Omed Betzad Sadehu. At this stage,
presumably it's because your standing allows you to keep the thing within
the field. That's what we're thinking now. Okay, we're going to change
that in a little later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Where do I know this idea that if it's ומנא תימא
דחצר שאינה משתמרת U’mina Teima Dechatzer She’eina Mishtameret if it's not protected,
יומד בצד שדהו אין אי לא לא, Yomed Betzad Sadehu Ein Ee
Lo Lo, only if you're standing by your field? דתניא, Detanya, we
learn in the ברייתא, Braita, היה עומד בעיר, Haya Omed Ba’ir, you
were in a city, you were in the town. I always say
city by עיר, Ir, but עיר Ir is a town; a כרך
Kerach is a city. Okay, you're in the town. היה עומד בעיר
Haya Omed Ba’ir ואומר, Ve’omer, יודע אני שעומר שיש לי בשדה, Yode’a
Ani She’omer Sheyesh Li Basadeh,
I know a sheaf that I have back in my field. I
left a sheaf in my field for the workers to gather it
up and I knew about that sheaf, and I know פועלים שכחוהו.
Po’alim Shachachuhu. I know that the workers are going to forget about
it, right? Like you know, they're not and that's therefore it's going
to be שכחה, Shichcha, because presumably when I'm not working in the
field and they're the ones that are supposed to be gathering it
in, if they leave the sheaf behind that's considered שכחה. Shichcha. So
here I am in the town, I'm feeling oh my god those
stupid workers, I forgot to tell them, you know, if I don't
tell them to remember to go to that other field off the
side that they're going to forget to do it. They're going to
forget that sheaf. Okay, I'm afraid they're going to forget their sheaf.
So you know what? לא יהא שכחה. Lo Yehei Shichcha. I am
here declaring that I remember the sheaf is there and it should
not be שכחה Shichcha because I'm not forgetting about it. So you
know what? The הלכה Halacha is, where am I? לא יהא שכחה.
Lo Yehei Shichcha. יכול לא יהא שכחה Yachol Lo Yehei Shichcha maybe
that works? תלמוד לומר ושכחת עומר בשדה. Talmud Lomar Veshachachta Omer Basadeh.
You forget it in the field. בשדה
ושכחת Basadeh Veshachachta ולא בעיר. Velo Ba’ir. Only forgetting in the field,
not in the town. And the גמרא Gemara, says one minute, that
sounds like even if you forgot it in the town, it's not
שכחה, Shichcha, which is the opposite, right? We're trying to say it
is שכחה. Shichcha. So the גמרא Gemara says: What does this mean?
Hold on. הגופא קשיא, Hagufa Kashya, this is internally contradictory. אמרת יכול
לא יהא שכחה, Amarta Yachol Lo Yehei Shichcha,
maybe in this case when I declare in the town that I
remembered it maybe it won't be, אלמא הרי זה שכחה. Alma Harei
Zeh Shichcha. Nevertheless, it is שכחה. Shichcha. ונסב לה גמרא, Venasiv La
Gemara, and then you learn take a learning,
a derivation from a פסוק, Pasuk, interesting use of the word גמרא
Gemara here. בשדה ושכחת Basadeh Veshachachta ולא בעיר. Velo Ba’ir.
Only forgetting in the field, not in the town. אלמא לא הוי
שכחה. Alma Lo Hevei Shichcha. It sounds like when you forget something
in the town it's not שכחה, Shichcha, but the whole point of
this was to say it was שכחה. Shichcha. אלא לאו הכי קאמר,
Ela Lav Hachi Ka’amar, here's how you have to read this ברייתא.
Braita. בשדה שכוח מעיקרא הוי שכחה. Basadeh Shachu’ach Me’ikara Hevei Shichcha. זכור
ולבסוף שכוח אין שכחה. Zachur Ulevasof Shachu’ach Ein Shichcha.
In the field, if it was something that I forgot initially, then
it is שכחה. Shichcha. If it's something that was remembered and then
forgotten in the end, it's not. Now what does remembered and forgotten
in the end mean? So Tosafot basically, Rashi and Tosafot says it
means that my workers forgot it but I still remember it. So
if I'm out there in the field with the workers, I told
them to go collect it, but I know it's there, so even
if they're, their forgetting is not, doesn't make it שכחה Shichcha as
long as I'm still aware that it's there and I'm still present
in the field. I'm going to go and tell them "What, did
you forget to do that? Go back and do that." I'm still
connected to the gathering. So my remembering is enough to prevent it
from being שכחה. Shichcha. So it's בשדה Basadeh is when it's only
if it's fully forgotten is it שכחה. Shichcha. But if I remember
it, it's not שכחה. Shichcha. Okay,
מאי טעמא, Mai Ta’ama, why is that? דכיון דקאי גבה, Dekivan Dekai
Gaba, since I'm still there out in the field, הוי ליה חצרו,
Hevei Lei Chatzero, it's my field, וזכתה לו, Vezachata Lo, and therefore
my field is reco-owned the sheaf for me. Now we're going to
get back to that because that is not how I would have
explained why it's not שכחה. Shichcha. Okay, אבל בל נסיים הפ..., Avel
Bal Nesayem Hapa..., okay, so let's finish the point. אבל בעיר, Avel
Ba’ir, if I remember in the town, אפילו זכור ולבסוף שכוח, Afilu
Zachur Ulevasof Shachu’ach, even if I'm still remembering but my workers are
forgetting, הוי שכחה. Hevei Shichcha. Even if it's not full שכחה, Shichcha,
I remember and they forget, that's still שכחה. Shichcha. Why? Because they're
the ones that are left with it in the field; their forgetting
makes
it
שכחה. Shichcha. מאי טעמא דליתא גבה, Mai Ta’ama Deleita Gaba, because the...
left them to do it and they forgot, who cares what I
know, it is שכחה. shikcha. But I would not explain it, I'm
not explaining it as my שדה sadeh is קונה, koneh it's the
question of who's in charge and who is supervising and who's doing
the act of gathering, so that their remembering or forgetting should be
relevant. I think that's the very logical way of explaining it. For
some reason the גמרא Gemara, says the reason it's not שכחה shikcha
when I am still there in the field with them
is somehow technically it is שכחה, shikcha, but because I'm standing in
my field, I'm automatically re-קונה koneh it. I don't get it, how
am I re-קונה koneh it? Once it's שכחה shikcha it belongs to
the עניים, aniyim, I'm not allowed to re-קונה koneh it. But I
guess what the גמרא Gemara is saying is not that I'm re-קונה
koneh it, but that I'm still holding on to it. Because I'm
standing in the field and somehow I still remember, it's like I'm
still possessing it and I'm not forgetting it. So understood that way
it's closer to what we were saying. If you're still there, but
let me give you a scenario. Let's say we're there in the
field and I'm going over to my next door neighbor to ask
for two eggs. And at that moment I'm knocking at my next
door neighbor's door and I'm twenty feet away and I know where
the sheaves are. At that moment they forget it, is it שכחה
shikcha because I'm not עומד בצד שדהו? omed b'tzad sadehu? According to
this גמרא, Gemara yeah, it's שכחה, shikcha, you weren't עומד בצד שדהו.
omed b'tzad sadehu. Again, I would think as long as I'm involved
and supervising and present, it's not שכחה. shikcha. But the גמרא Gemara
is saying no, no, no, it's because if you're standing in the
field, it's like you're still holding on to it. So that's the
גמרא's Gemara proof that if it's a חצר שאינה משתמרת, chatzer she'eina
mishtameres, because here's by the way the difference. A חצר is a
yard. Your yard is classically משתמרת, mishtameres, you got a fence around
your yard. A שדה sadeh is out there in the field with
all the grain. You ever drive by and you see miles and
miles and miles of the standing corn or whatever? It's not משתמרת.
mishtameres. People don't put a fence around their big fields of grain.
So therefore the שדה sadeh is a classic case of אינה משתמרת.
eina mishtameres. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says, ah, you see, and
it's only going to work if you're standing there, if you're in
the town it doesn't work, if you're standing there it does work,
and that's the idea that your physical presence even אינה משתמרת eina
mishtameres makes it like you're holding and possessing it. Yes?
When,
how, at what point does the forgetting kick in? Is it like
I'm harvesting and I leave something behind and then it's שכחה? shikcha?
At the end of the day we look around and...
No, it was left, right, so you're right. The scenario I gave,
oh, they're going to forget that one off at the side, that
wasn't actually an accurate scenario. We're about to see in a minute,
it's not something you forgot to do, it's something that you left
it behind. So you actually went through that section and you forgot
it behind.
Even
if at the end of that
whatever field you're going to look around and get anything that you...
That's an interesting question. Like if you plant... your plan
is the way you work is you do it one path and
then you go back and you do another path and
you haven't, in your mind you're not done. Part of your process
is then you go back and look it over? Yeah, that's an
interesting question. I don't know the answer to that. All right, so
let's take a look. Anyway the גמרא Gemara learns from this, we
could have easily explained it much more about who's in charge, but
the גמרא Gemara learns from this that if you're present and in
the field it's like you're still possessing it. So now the גמרא
Gemara, nevertheless challenges even this read. גמרא Gemara says ממאי, mimai, who
told you that's the way to read
this ברייתא, braisa, דילמא dilma or how is the ברייתא braisa necessarily
reading the פסוק pasuk this way? דילמא גזירת הכתוב הוא, dilma g'zeiras
hakasuv hu, maybe the פסוק pasuk is like it sounds like, should
be read like it sounds like. דבשדה הוי שכחה, d'basadeh havei shikcha,
that if you forget in the field it counts, בעיר לא הוי
שכחה. ba'ir lo havei shikcha. If you're forgetting while you're in the
city, maybe it's the opposite of what we said. Maybe it's not
שכחה, shikcha, only when you're in the field is your forgetting meaningful.
Your forgetting
in the town isn't meaningful. No, אמר קרא, amar kra, we know
that's not true, לא תשוב לקחתו, lo sashuv l'kachto, the extra verse,
do not return to take it, לרבות שכחת העיר, l'rabos shikchas ha'ir,
even if that means while you forgot in the city, that's a
real לא תשוב, lo sashuv, don't go back to your field back
to the country in order to take it. So therefore we know
forgetting in the town actually is שכחה. shikcha. גמרא says, one minute,
that's not what that פסוק pasuk is telling you. האי מבעי ליה
ללאו, hai mibei lei l'lav, that פסוק pasuk is telling you that
if you go back and take the sheaf, you transgress a negative
prohibition. No, אי הכי נימא קרא, i hachi neima kra, if that's
all the פסוק pasuk was saying, let it say לא תקחנו, lo
sikachenu, don't take it. מאי לא תשוב, mai lo sashuv, do not
return? לרבות שכחת העיר, l'rabos shikchas ha'ir, that even if you're in
the town and you forget that counts as שכחה shikcha and don't
return back to the field. One minute, says גמרא, והא האי מבעי
ליה לכדתנן, v'ha hai mibei lei l'chid'tenan, how about this other teaching
which is exactly what we were just discussing?
שלפניו אין שכחה, she'lifanav ein shikcha, if you forgot to do something
that's still in front of you, you were supposed to do that
next field over or gather the
sheaves in that side lot and you forgot about it that that
was your job. Okay,
that's not שכחה. shikcha. שלאחריו שכחה, she'le'acharav shikcha, what you left behind
you, that you passed through that space and you were... supposed to
collect it and you didn't, so in that case יש שכחה, yesh
shikcha, there is. שהוא בבל תשוב. shehu b'bal tashuv. How do we
know? Because it says לא תשוב לקחתו, lo tashuv lekachto, don't go
back to collect it. So if it's something that I left behind
me, it's שכחה, shikcha, not something that I have yet to do.
So anyway, neither of those are telling you the idea that forgetting
in the town counts as forgetting. So גמרא says זה הכלל, zeh
haklal, let's just finish the משנה, this is the principle: כל שהוא
בבל תשוב שכחה, kol shehu b'val tashuv shikcha, anything that would fall
under the rubric of 'do not return' constitutes שכחה. shikcha. כל שאינו
בבל תשוב, kol sheino b'val tashuv, if it's not 'don't return' because
you haven't gotten to it yet, אינו שכחה. eino shikcha. So anyway,
לא תשוב לקחתו lo tashuv lekachto is to tell you a negative
prohibition and tell you how to define שכחה, shikcha, but it is
not telling you this idea that forgetting in the town counts. So
how do you know to begin with the idea that forgetting in
the town counts? So אמר רב אשי אמר קרא amar Rav Ashi
amar kra because the verse says יהיה. yihiyeh. It says it says
like לגר ליתום ולאלמנה יהיה, lager layatom v'la'almanah yihiyeh, it should be.
The ריבוי שכחת עיר, ribui shikchat ir, so the extra emphasis they
have it tells me even if it's something that you didn't forget
when you were in the field but you forgot when you were
out in the town, even that counts. וכן, v'chein, okay, anyway, that's
the end of the שכחה shikcha discussion. But the point is, based
on this idea of שכחה shikcha which seems to be a weak
analogy, but the גמרא is saying because when you're in the field
as long as you remember even if your workers forget, it's not
שכחה, shikcha, that shows standing in a חצר אינה משתמרת chatzer einah
mishtameret is like possessing, is like holding onto it. But if you're
not standing there and it's אינה משתמרת, einah mishtameret, you're not holding
onto it. Okay? וכן, v'chein, and then so now we're going to
get back to that main point. We're putting שכחה shikcha behind us.
Haha. Okay, we're leaving it behind. וכן אמר עולא והוא שעומד בצד
שדהו, v'chein amar Ulla v'hu she'omed b'tzad sadeh, it only works to
be קונה koneh this צבי tzvi running through your yard if you're
standing there. וכן אמר רבה בר בר חנה והוא שעומד בצד שדהו.
v'chein amar Rabbah bar bar Chana v'hu she'omed b'tzad sadeh. Okay, now,
איבעיא, ibaia, by the way, here's an interesting question even within this
concept of משתמרת. mishtameret.
משתמרת mishtameret from whom? Let's say it's not a צבי tzvi that's
in my yard, let's say somebody accidentally dropped a wallet in my
yard or twenty dollars or whatever, wallet probably has a סימן. siman.
Okay, the twenty dollars isn't going anywhere on its own. Okay, so
it's not going to leave my yard on its own. Okay, but
somebody could walk into my yard and pick it up. Is that
considered משתמרת mishtameret or לא משתמרת? lo mishtameret? And do I also
have to be able to protect it from outside people? That would
make sense, right? So and so presumably standing by the field accomplishes
two things: it prevents the thing from going out and prevents other
people from coming in. If I've got a fence around it, I
don't need to be standing, but without a fence I need to
be standing. Okay? And again, right now we're assuming it all is
working based on the need to define it as משתמרת. mishtameret. Let's
continue.
Okay. איתיביה רב אבא לעולא. eitiveih Rav Abba l'Ulla. רב אבא Rav
Abba challenged עולא Ulla that said you needed to be standing by
it.
מעשה ברבן גמליאל וזקנים שהיו באין בספינה. ma'aseh b'Rabban Gamliel u'zekeinim she'hayu
ba'in b'sefinah. There's all these good stories of where people, these Rabbis
were on boats. It's interesting whole discussion of why were the Rabbis
always traveling on boats? Sometimes it was actually because they were making,
you know, presenting the case of the Jewish community to the Caesars
or whatever. There's interesting literature on that. Anyway, they were coming on
a boat. אמר רבן גמליאל. amar Rabban Gamliel. So רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel said, עישור שאני עתיד למוד, isur she'ani atid lamod, the מעשר
ma'aser that I'm going to I'm going to measure out, נתון ליהושע,
natun l'Yehoshua, is given to יהושע. Yehoshua. יהושע Yehoshua was a לוי
Levi and he was on the boat with him, רב יהושע. Reb
Yehoshua. ומקומו מושכר לו, u'mekomo mushkar lo, and I'm renting the space
to him so it's like I've given it to him now. So
תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion, like why was he doing this?
רש"י Rashi says in a not here, in another גמרא, that he
had left his house without separating תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot and he
was afraid that the people of his house would eat the grain
and he didn't want them to be eating טבל. tevel. So he
was separating out the תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot from a distance. Okay.
But תוספות Tosafot questions that. Like תוספות Tosafot questions: A, they wouldn't
have assumed that it was separated out; and B, he doesn't sound
like he's saying that I am going to be מפריש mafrish the
מעשר. ma'aser. It's not sounding like he's separating the מעשר ma'aser now,
he's saying 'I'm going to measure it out.' Also, why is there
a need to give the מעשר ma'aser to the לוי Levi right
away? If you just want to save your family from eating טבל,
tevel, you just say, you know, ten percent on the north corner
of the grain is מעשר, ma'aser, the next ten percent or the
ten percent on the south corner is מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. Right?
Why are you having to say that I'm going to, you know,
why do you have to transfer it to the לוי? Levi? So
תוספות Tosafot says that actually it's not a case of separating מעשר
ma'aser and stopping it from being טבל, tevel, it's actually a case
we just learned recently in the תורה Torah about at the end
of three years you have to get rid of all the תרומות
ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot you haven't distributed yet. So he actually had מעשר
ma'aser in his house that he had separated, but he hadn't distributed
it yet. So he's actually trying now to give it, to distribute,
not physically, but to transfer the ownership. Okay, so he's transferring the
ownership to this לוי Levi who's on the ship. Alright, one way
or the other, it doesn't really I mean, it's an interesting תרומות
ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot question, but for us what matters is, is he
successfully transferring the ownership? Okay? So he has this מעשר ma'aser he's
either now separating or that's been separated and he's
saying 'I'm going
to...' And the end of this משנה actually is and Yehoshua gave
him like a dollar, it didn't say a dollar, and he rented
the piece of the land under the grain and therefore the מעשר
Maaser was transferred to Yehoshua. Okay. The איסור אחר, issur acher,
the second מעשר maaser that I'm going to measure out, which is
מעשר עני maaser ani in this case, נתן לעקיבא בן יוסף, nasan
l'Akiva ben Yosef, is given to עקיבא בן יוסף Akiva ben Yosef
כדי שיזכו בו עניים. kedei sheyizku vo aniyim. He was a גבאי
עניים gabbai aniyim and he should take possession of it for the
עניים. aniyim. And how do I transfer ownership to him? ומקומו מושכר
לו umekomo muskar lo and I'm renting the space underneath the grain
to him and then he paid a dollar and then he took
possession of it. Okay, they did all this on the boat. Okay,
so now the גמרא says, וכי רבי יהושע ורבי עקיבא בצד שדהו
של רבן גמליאל היו עומדים? vechi Rabbi Yehoshua veRabbi Akiva betzad sadehu
shel Rabban Gamliel hayu omdim? How could they be קונה koneh. with
a קניין חצר, kinyan chatzer, right? Presumably it's out in the field.
Right, you asked an interesting question. Is it out in the field
or is it in the house? תוספות Tosafos asks the extra question:
if it's in a house, what does משתמרת mishtameres mean? If the
family thinks it all belongs to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and they're
going to take it thinking it belongs to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
is it considered משתמרת mishtameres even though the house is protected from
outsiders? If I now have a, renting a little square foot in
your house that's mine, but nobody in your house knows it's my
square foot and they don't know the stuff in this is mine,
is that considered משתמרת mishtameres because people are just going to take,
the people in the house are going to take the stuff from
my little plot of land that I've now rented in your house?
So תוספות Tosafos anyway asks those interesting questions. Even if this is
out in the field or even if this is in a house,
it might not be משתמרת mishtameres because the people, the family doesn't
know that it belongs to עקיבא Akiva and it's not protected from
the family members. So how did this, how did this piece of
land work? They weren't standing by it. Okay. וכי רבי יהושע ורבי
עקיבא בצד שדהו של רבן גמליאל היו עומדים? vechi Rabbi Yehoshua veRabbi
Akiva betzad sadehu shel Rabban Gamliel hayu omdim? Were they standing by
his field? So you see you don't need עומד בצד שדהו. omed
betzad sadehu. Even if it's a חצר שאינה משתמרת chatzer she'eina mishtameres
and non-protected field, it works even without standing by it, because this
was a case that the field was not protected and the grain
was on it and they were קונה koneh it even though they
were not standing on it. Yes?
Wait, so they were, I thought they were, he said something about
like renting it instead?
He's renting them, yeah. קניין חצר kinyan chatzer works even if you're
just a renter of the field. You don't have to be an
owner of the field. So therefore they now own, rent, right? Inside
of it. They now temporarily own because they're renting the field, so
they should be able to be קונה koneh the stuff that's in
the field, or you know, that's in that square foot that's theirs,
right? So the גמרא says, well why is that work? They're not
standing by it and it's not משתמרת, mishtameres, right? Either it's not
משתמרת mishtameres because it's out in the field or it's not משתמרת
mishtameres because the family doesn't realize it's there, so it's not protected
from the family members. Okay, so yes they rented it. Right. I
forgot to make that point. If you own a space, if you're
renting a space, you can also use it to be קונה קניין
חצר koneh kinyan chatzer because you're seen like a temporary owner of
that space.
When so in general I rent your backyard and there's a bicycle
back there, you're קונה.
koneh. If you're, if you're renting my apartment, if you're renting my
apartment, then anything that falls into that apartment, you're קונה koneh with
your קניין חצר, kinyan chatzer, not me. Okay. For as long as
the rental agreement. For as long as the rental agreement.
Then if I've taken the bike elsewhere, it now belongs back to
the owner?
No, no, no. If it's a מציאה, metzia, no, no, you own
it permanently. As long as it's during the rental agreement, a מציאה
metzia falls into, into the apartment that I've rented you, you own
it 100 percent, you know, for eternity. But I'm not there.
Like, no, no, no. You own, you don't have a right to
take possession.
Like I can be staying at someone's house but I can't like
קונה all of their stuff.
Right, because
you're still not allowed, you're still not allowed to steal. Okay, it
works as a קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer. Okay. Now the גמרא says
like this, okay. Now, וכי
רבי יהושע ורבי עקיבא בצד שדהו של רבן גמליאל היו עומדים? vechi
Rabbi Yehoshua veRabbi Akiva betzad sadehu shel Rabban Gamliel hayu omdim? So
nevertheless it was קונה. You see you don't need עומד בצד שדהו.
omed betzad sadehu. אמר ליה, amar lei, so עולא Ulla said back,
דמי האי מרבנן דלא גמר אינשי שמעתא. dami hai merabbanan dela gmar
inshi shmaita. It sounds like to me like you've never done any
real learning, which is a nice way of avoiding answering the question.
You know we've had this before in the גמרא that somebody says
like what a stupid question and refuses to answer and it's not
such a stupid question. So now, so now כי אתא לסורא, ki
ata l'Sura, so you know רבי אבא Rabbi Abba who asked the
question and עולא Ulla just pushed him off, he was not satisfied,
he was looking for an answer. So when he came to סורא,
Sura, אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to the people in the
ישיבה, yeshiva, הכי אמר עולא, hachi amar Ulla, here's what עולא Ulla
said, he said you need to be standing by the field, והכי
אותיבתי, ve'hachi osivtei, and I challenged him by this case, by the
case of the מעשר, maaser, and he didn't give me an answer.
אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן, amar lei hahu merabbanan, so one of the
rabbis of the ישיבה yeshiva said to him, here's the answer to
that, why that wasn't a challenge. רבן גמליאל מטלטלי אגב מקרקעי הקנה
להם. Rabban Gamliel mataltlei agav mekarkei hikna lahem. So he was not
transferring the מעשר maaser by a קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer. You know
how he was transferring the מעשר? maaser? By a קניין אגב. kinyan
agav. Okay, you might remember from קידושין, Kiddushin,
if I, no listen, because you don't. I can, if you take
possession of a piece, if I give you... If I give you
a piece of property of landed property, as when you take possession
of that piece of land, you can also take possession of any
מטלטלין. metaltelin. It doesn't even have to be on the land. And
it's not operating as חצר. It's operating as the act of possessing
the land is an act of possessing any other מטלטלין metaltelin I
want to bundle with it. Okay? So therefore the problem is it
said מקומו מושכר לו, mekomo mushkar lo, because you could have just
rented him any random piece of land. Okay? But what this answer
is saying, that's לאו דווקא. lav davka. So it wasn't a קניין
חצר. kinyan chatzer. By renting יהושע Yehoshua a piece of land, that's
like an act of possessing the land. Actually, there's something which also
might help in understanding why renting works for קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer.
רמב"ם Rambam says a rental agreement is a קניין גוף לפירות לזמן.
kinyan guf le-peiros li-zman. Very nice לומדות. lumdus. This is what you
wouldn't have expected from רמב"ם. Rambam. You own it for its use,
it's an ownership for its use, for the use of using it
for a limited period of time, for the year. You've rented it
for the year. So it's an ownership of the property for its
פירות, peiros, for its use, for a limited period of time. It's
a type of ownership. So if you understand it that way, and
that certainly fits with this, so when I rent you something, you're
taking limited possession of it. Since you're taking possession of it, you
can take possession of any other מטלטלין metaltelin I want to include.
So it didn't really have to be sitting on it, and it
wasn't a קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So you don't need to be
standing בצד שדהו, be-tzad sadeh, and you don't need מסמרת. mismeres. You
just need to possess the land, and that's why it worked.
It makes sense because the מעשר ma'aser wasn't a מציאה metzia to
begin with.
But I have my דעת da'at, to transfer it. I'm the owner
of this grain, right? Okay. So you either need to, again, still
no stealing. You either need it to be a מציאה metzia or
the owner to be transferring. Okay. So that was the answer. That's
why it's not a proof for קניין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So the
גמרא says רבי זירא קיבלה. Rabbi Zeira kiblah. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
thought that was a good response. רבי אבא לא קיבלה. Rabbi Abba
lo kiblah. רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, who was the one who challenged
עולא, Ulla, was not satisfied. That is not an acceptable response. אמר
רבא שפיר עביד דלא קיבלה. Amar Rava shapir avid d'la kiblah. רבי
אבא Rabbi Abba was right to refuse to accept that as a
way of explaining this. Why? Because we're not talking about a קניין
אגב. kinyan agav. If all they wanted to do was a קניין
אגב, kinyan agav, there were other ways... if they weren't doing a
קניין חצר, kinyan chatzer, there were other ways they could have transferred
the grain. So what would be another way they could have transferred?
וכי לא היה להם סודר לקנות ממנו בחליפין? ve-chi lo hayah lahem
sudar liknos mimenu be-chalipin? So just, what, you couldn't find a handkerchief?
If all you wanted to do was do some קניין kinyan other
than חצר, why are you doing בקנייה דארעא bikneih de-ar'a and with
בקנייה דארעא bikneih de-ar'a I'm קונה the grain? Just do like a
חליפין. chalipin. Give a handkerchief. You know, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua should
give רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel a handkerchief and in exchange רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel will transfer over the grain. Okay, so but that raises
a good question: Why didn't they do that? So you've proven there
were other קניינים kinyanim available. Why didn't they do the other קניינים?
kinyanim? So we're going to hear the answer. So the גמרא says
אלא וכי לא היה להם סודר לקנות ממנו בחליפין אלא... ela ve-chi
lo hayah lahem sudar liknos mimenu be-chalipin ela... here's why other forms
of קניין kinyan would not have worked. טובת הנאה אינה ממון לקנות
ממנו בחליפין. tovat hana'ah einah mamon liknos mimenu be-chalipin. הכא
נמי טובת הנאה אינה ממון לקנות אגב קרקע. hacha nami tovat hana'ah
einah mamon liknos agav karka. What does it mean? It means רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel does not own the מעשר. ma'aser. Okay? Who owns
the מעשר? ma'aser? Well, nobody owns the מעשר, ma'aser, or the לויים
Leviyim own the מעשר. ma'aser. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel only has a
טובת הנאה. tovat hana'ah. He has a right to choose which לוי
Levi to give it to, but he doesn't own it. When can
I transfer something to you with a קניין אגב? kinyan agav? If
I sell you land, I can give you other things. When can
I transfer something קניין חליפין? kinyan chalipin? If I am giving you
my object. I am transferring ownership of my object. That's not the
relationship רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel has to this מעשר. ma'aser. The relationship
he has is it's not his, he has the right to give
it to somebody, but he doesn't own it. If he doesn't own
it, he can't transfer the ownership. You know the only thing he
can do? He can't transfer ownership, he can only give it. So
what's giving it? Well, giving it is I'm handing it to you.
You know what another giving it is? I'm putting it in your
yard, right?
So that he can do. You can put it in somebody's hand,
you can put it in somebody's yard. That's what it means to
give the מעשר. ma'aser. But you can't transfer ownership by חליפין chalipin
or transfer ownership by a קניין אגב kinyan agav because you don't
have ownership in the first place to transfer. I don't get it.
You don't get it at all?
Just hear it. I can hold it in my hand... right, but
there's two different forms of giving.
No, let's imagine... let's imagine we were talking about a bill of
sale, okay?
If you write a שטר...
shetar... you think you could write a שטר? shetar? If I go
ahead and I give you this... let's say I say to you,
דב, Dov, you know, here's my iPhone, okay? I'm feeling very generous,
it's עשרת ימי תשובה Aseret Yemei Teshuvah and I waste too much
time on it anyway. I want you to give it to the
first עני ani that you find, okay? So just give it to
them. So you find an עני. ani. Would you be able to
like write him out a שטר? shetar? You can't write him a
שטר, shetar, you don't own it, right? You could give it to
him and then you're sort of acting as my שליח and you're
giving it to him, but you can't give it to him in
a שטר. shetar. So you can't do a קניין kinyan that is
about transferring ownership if you're not the one who owns it. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel doesn't own the מעשר, ma'aser, so he can't do
a קניין that focuses on transferring ownership.
If I had an iPhone and
I give it to an עני, ani,
so it's not my iPhone...
no, no, it's totally mine. You just have the right to give
it to an עני, ani, but you can't write a bill of
sale because it would need to be yours for you to write
a bill of sale. You can't give the מעשר maaser in a
way that is about transferring ownership.
You could see it like that. I mean, it's a טובת הנאה.
tovat hana'ah. He has the right to decide which of the ten
thousand עניים aniyim or the ten thousand לויים leviyim he's going to
designate it for. But it's not his. He just has a right
to designate one of those לויים leviyim to receive it. So you
can do that by an act of physically handing it over, but
you can't do that by something which is about transferring ownership. You
don't have the ownership to transfer.
Like a שטר shtar or a
קנין סודר?
kinyan
sudar? Right. So you understand the distinction if he has already set
aside the מעשר maaser and now he's just giving the ability to
transfer to the לוי Levi of his choice. But here, he does
own it until he says, I'm making this מעשר maaser and giving
it to you.
Okay, so that might depend on, so I hear that, that might
depend on the debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot
says the מעשר maaser was already taken. He's just giving it. רש״י
Rashi says you're also being מפריש mafrish the מעשר. maaser. Now even
there I would say, what?
It's pretty clear he would...
הוא עתיד למוד. hu atid limod. עתיד למוד. atid limod. No, not
עתיד להפריש. atid lehafrish. עתיד למוד. atid limod. Okay, I'm going to
measure out. Okay, anyway, we could talk about it more, but anyway,
but I would say even according to you, he owns the טבל.
tevel. But once he's מפריש mafrish it, he doesn't own the resulting
מעשר. maaser. It's a two-step thing. Yeah. Okay. Yeah.
We're kind of back to the גט, right?
The question is giving versus being transferring ownership. Yeah, that's a good
parallel. Okay, so that's why it said, look, he didn't do a
סודר sudar because it's not about transferring ownership. And that's why you
can't tell me קנין אגב. kinyan agav. The only thing you could
do is hand it to the guy or put it in the
guy's חצר. So we're talking about קנין חצר kinyan chatzer and it
is a good proof that קנין חצר kinyan chatzer does not need
you to be standing by your field. Okay, so let's take a
look. So the גמרא says, אינה עומדת בצד שדהו. eina omedet betzad
sadehu. ולא היא, velo hi, says the גמרא, מתנות כהונה נתינה כתיבא
בהו. matnot kehunah netinah ketivah behu. That's not the reason you actually
can't do an act of transferring ownership. So why couldn't you do
a קנין סודר? kinyan sudar? You could just do חליפין? chalifin? No,
there's another reason you couldn't do חליפין. chalifin. Because it says ונתת,
venatata, you have to give it, meaning it has to be given
as a gift. And the fundamental act of חליפין chalifin is fundamentally
an exchange, it's not a gift. That's what חליפין chalifin is based
on. So מתנות כהונה... matnot kehunah... חליפין דרך מקח וממכר הוא. chalifin
derech mekach umimkar hu. חליפין chalifin is a type of business transaction,
an exchange. So you can't use חליפין chalifin to give. מטלטלין אגב
מקרקעי, metaltelin agav mekarkai, but to transfer chattel with transferring land, נתינה
למיקרי, netinah lemikrei, that is a giving. Okay, so therefore he, I
said it was a lovely answer, but the גמרא says no, we
can still say you can't do חליפין, chalifin, but you could do
a קנין אגב kinyan agav and it is not a קנין חצר
kinyan chatzer here. It is a giving. You can transfer ownership as
long as it's through a gifting. And therefore it works as אגב,
agav, it's not חצר, it's not a relevant case for חצר. Let's
just read one more answer to this. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa
amar, no, you know why that didn't need עומד בצד שדהו? omed
betzad sadehu? That was חצר. But you know why it didn't need
it? Because דעת אחרת מקנה אותן שאני. da'at acheret maknah otan shani.
Because if you have a gift, if you have somebody that is
actively providing the דעת, da'at actively giving it, you don't need as
strong of a קנין. kinyan. Every קנין kinyan constitutes two components: the
דעת da'at, to transfer ownership, to possess it, and the physical act
that represents that I am taking possession. The more you have דעת,
da'at. the less you need the strength of the act. Like before
we discussed, a קטן might not be able to קונה מציאה, koneh
metziah, but he might be able to do it with somebody else's
דעת. da'at Okay, so if you have a מציאה metziah might require,
right, that you have a stronger sense of possessing it, the חצר
משתמרת, chatzer mishtameret, I'm standing or I'm standing in my field, I'm
more strongly possessing it. If you're giving it to me and you
are directing this gift to me, it's not free for anybody to
take. I am giving this to דוב, Dov, I only want this
to go to דוב, Dov, then I can do a smaller act
of showing that it's mine, as long as it's in my field
even if I'm not fully holding it, I'm not standing and it's
not משתמרת, mishtameret, a weaker act suffices when you are giving it
to me and your דעת da'at, is directed towards me. Okay, does
that make sense to people? The stronger the דעת, da'at and particularly
the fact that the דעת is directed towards me as opposed to
a מציאה, metziah, allows me to do an act that's not as
strong. Alright, so we'll continue with more of this tomorrow.